said, "Welcome back." And in the
previous producer setup video, I ended
up with telling you one problem
uh when we choose max in-flight requests
per connection greater than one and
retry greater than zero.
So, the issue which I mentioned was
message reordering problem.
So, today we will go one level more
deeper into it and see the solution.
So, the problem one.
Let's understand with this flow of the
duplicate message problem.
Now, let's say producer send one batch
which has let's say for example, this
batch has only one event in it. Okay?
Now, broker receive this batch and in
the log it will write
event one
written at offset one. Okay? Let's say
this batch has only one event in it.
And it send the acknowledgement which
get lost because of some network issue.
Now, producer will wait for some time
and since retry is greater than zero,
after some time it will retry it. Okay?
The same batch is sent again.
Now, the broker receive it again and it
will write the same event at let's say
offset two. Now, at this point of time
in a log
there is a duplicate. Same event appear
multiple times.
Okay? Because today broker has no way to
determine it has already written
the same
event before or not. So, that is the
problem one when we have a retry.
There is a chance that duplicate
messages get recorded into the logs.
Another is message reordering issue.
So, when we have
max in-flight requests per connection
greater than one, means more than one
packets we can send over the connection.
Even though they are in-flight, means
broker is still working on it, means
there There no acknowledgement sent.
Okay? So now in that scenario what uh
problem can come? Let's say producer
sent two batches.
Batch one, batch two.
Both are in flight. Okay?
Now for now assume that these two
batches has only one one event. Event
one here in the batch one, event two
there in the batch two.
Now because of some issue, network
issue, this batch one never reached till
broker.
And
this
batch two is now reaching first at the
broker.
So what would happen in the log file? It
will write event two written at offset
one.
Event two written at offset one.
It will send an acknowledgement for the
batch two.
Now producer will wait for the
acknowledgement for the batch one.
But it will wait for some time. After
that it didn't come, so it will retry it
and it will send the batch one again.
Now the broker will write
event one.
Event one at offset two.
Now here if you see that
See, in the batch one let's say event
one, batch two, event two. Event one
let's say order created, event two is
like payment made.
But what in the logs got stored? Event
two at offset one. Means this happened
before. Means you made a payment
earlier.
Event one which is order created, that
happened after.
That is wrong.
Okay?
So it's like order is paid before even
it is created.
So there is a message reordering issue
comes. Because broker today do not have
a way
to know that hey, whatever the events I
am getting
or whatever the batch I am getting, you
can say that that is a more proper way.
Whatever the batches I am getting
am I getting in the sequence order or
not?
There is no way
broker can identify it today.
So, what is the solution for it? Both
the problem.
The solution is
setting the idempotency equals to true.
In the producer application.properties,
we need to set
spring.kafka.producer.properties.enable
idempotency equals to true.
So, if you are using Kafka version less
than three,
then by default it is false and we have
to make it true.
But, if you are using Kafka version
greater than equals to three, it is by
default true. So, we don't have to worry
about it.
So, what happened internally? We can say
that, okay, if you use idempotency
equals to true,
these two problems will get resolved.
But, how? That is the interesting thing,
right?
So,
step one.
We have uh starting the producer
application.
First time we are starting the producer
What would happen?
Producer will go to any broker,
bootstrap server, any broker, "Hey, give
me some unique ID."
Now, broker will go to the controller,
pass the same request that producer is
asking for unique ID.
Controller will generate one
PID, producer ID. Okay.
Whatever the next So, it just maintain a
sequence number. In the next sequence
number, let's say till 1,000 is used, it
will just increment one, 1,001. So, it
will return that, "Hey,
this is the new unique ID."
But, this unique ID is nowhere stored at
this point of time.
It just computed and returned it. And
the broker returned this unique ID to
producer.
So, in a step one, when we start the
producer application,
producer now has one PID.
Let's say 1001.
Okay?
Step two, producer send the request to
the broker. What would happen? So, in
the producer setup, I told you already.
There are multiple stages, right? We
have serializer, we have partitioner, we
have record accumulator.
Now, in record accumulator, I told that
batches are created
topic and partition wise. Okay? So,
multiple batch, let's say topic A
partition zero, topic A partition one,
topic B partition zero. So, for each
topic partition wise, batch is created.
Okay? And events are accumulated within
it.
Now,
when idempotency is set to true,
this three information is more added.
What is that?
One is PID, whatever we have got into
the step one.
The producer ID, that is added.
The base sequence, okay? For each topic
and partition, a sequence is maintained,
you can say.
Okay? Let's say
topic A partition zero, some sequence is
maintained.
Okay? Similarly, topic A partition one,
sequence is maintained. Individual
sequence is maintained.
Let's say 0 1 2 3 4, it is maintaining
its own sequence.
For topic A partition one, its own
maintained sequence. Okay?
So, sequence is maintained topic
partition wise.
So, now this let's say this is the first
time batches are created,
so base sequence is zero.
And last sequence is two.
So,
with each event which are stored in this
batch, is assigned a sequence number.
Event one,
sequence zero. Event two, sequence one.
Event three, sequence two.
Okay? So,
if I repeat it again,
record accumulator, create a batch topic
partition wise.
Okay?
And it also, for each event it add, it
also append a sequence number.
Okay? And
once the batch is created, it also add
that what is the base sequence number?
Means the starting
sequence zero. And what is the last
sequence? Two.
Okay? Sequence two is the last.
Similarly,
for batch two, topic A partition one,
it has only two events. So, when event
eight is stored here,
it is assigned let's say sequence zero.
Event nine, sequence one.
So, pros uh producer ID,
base sequence zero,
and the last sequence is one.
Similarly, batch three for topic B
partition zero, it will maintain its own
sequence.
So, it has currently four events.
Each event is assigned a sequence
number. Event one, sequence zero. Event
two, sequence one. Event three, sequence
two. Event four, sequence three.
So, this is the producer ID.
Base sequence is zero, and the last
sequence is three.
So, this three additional information is
added with each batch. You can say that
this is a header information of the
batch.
And now this is compressed and
ultimately sent to the broker.
Okay?
So,
step two is clear? Producer send the
request.
Now, with this batch,
producer ID, PID,
base sequence,
means event
with the
starting sequence number, and the last
sequence means last event what is its
sequence number.
That is added and sent.
Now, step three, the batch received by
the broker, what would happen?
Now, let's say the first time the
request received from producer to
broker.
Now, producer is sending the batch to
the broker.
Okay? Now, this batch has
let's say batch one. This is for topic
A,
partition P0.
I have this process ID. This is the
process ID which is at has this. And
this batch has base sequence zero. Means
this event one is
sequence zero. And the last sequence is
two. So, in this batch, there could be
multiple events. So, the last event has
this sequence.
This information is sent to the broker.
Now, broker, what it will do?
Broker maintain in memory map
for
topic
partition-wise.
Okay?
So, now it will check
in memory map. Hey, for this process ID,
PID
1001. So, for this process ID
for this
for this producer ID, for this topic and
this partition,
what is the next sequence number I am
expecting?
So, see, this is the first time producer
is sending the request. So, we are
seeing the flow first request. So,
definitely broker doesn't have any batch
doesn't have any in memory information.
So, no map found at this point of time.
So, when no map found means for this
process ID, for this
for this producer ID, for this producer
ID,
for whatever the topic, whatever the
partition,
okay?
This is the first request I am getting.
Okay? So, my expected is that this batch
should have a base sequence zero.
Okay? This is my expectation. It should
sequence should be from zero. See
See, order should be maintained 0 1 2 3
4 like this.
So, when the first request come, the
sequence should be zero.
Okay? Now, it will check. Okay, this
batch has base sequence zero? Yes.
It is accepted. And it will create a map
in memory map. Hey, process ID is 1001.
Topic is A.
Topic is A. Partition is P0.
What is the last sequence I have read?
Till two.
Okay, till two, I am done.
Now, let's say the next batch is sending
by the producer.
Second request. Let's say batch two it
is sending.
Topic A.
Partition P0. PID, base sequence, last
sequence. Let's say this is the
scenario.
What broker will do? It will check in
memory.
Hey, for this process ID
for this topic and this partition
topic A
partition P0
what is the next sequence I am
expecting?
Okay? So, it will check its memory map.
So,
in the step one, we have created a map,
right?
Process ID, topic, partition.
Okay? So, process ID, topic, partition,
it get.
Okay?
Uh
producer ID is 1001 1001.
Topic A.
Partition P0. Yes, a map found. What is
the next sequence? Next sequence is last
sequence till it read is two. Next
sequence is two plus one. Hey, I am
expecting the base sequence which you
are sending, it should be start with
three.
So, in the map in this batch header, the
base sequence should be start with
three.
If this is the case, this batch will get
accepted. Otherwise,
this batch will get rejected. And the
producer will have to retry.
And it will update the map.
Producer ID 1001, topic is A, partition
P0 till
what I have successfully last sequence
read five.
So it will update till five.
I have got it.
Okay, the next time
the batch will come
it will check the same map.
Okay, this is the producer ID. This is
the topic. This is the partition it want
to write. The next time expecting is
five plus one.
The next time expecting the base
sequence should be starting from six
only because till five I am done.
Okay.
Till five I have written the events.
The next I should be getting six. So the
next batch whatever it should be base
sequence should be six.
Then only it will accept the
batch.
Got it?
Now with this
both duplicate and message ordering
issue is fixed. Okay.
Now let's first try to see the demo of
it. Like here
let me
zoom it a bit.
Let me first clean up
uh
everything controller so that we will
start from controller
one dot logs removed.
Controller two dot logs removed.
Broker one dot logs removed. Broker two
logs removed. Everything is removed.
What we have to do next is creating a
unique ID.
So we will create a unique cluster ID.
So this is the cluster ID new.
Now we have to attach two broker two
controller with this cluster ID.
Uh so here
controller one
I have to just copy this new cluster ID
and update it.
So here with the controller one, I have
updated with this new cluster ID.
Similarly, controller two also
appended with this new cluster ID.
Now broker one
broker one also done with this cluster
ID broker two.
So now two broker, two controller are
now associated with one cluster. So they
all belong to one cluster. That is done.
Now what we have to do is we have to
start the servers. So now let's start
the server for
>> [snorts]
>> controller one. So this is Kafka server
start we are starting.
And here we will start for controller
two.
So
start here, start here.
So I have started both the controllers.
So controllers are started. Okay? Now we
have to start the broker.
We have to start the broker here.
Let me open a new tab.
We have to start the broker. So I am
starting
broker one
in this one
and I'm starting broker two here.
So both the clusters started
and both the broker are started. Okay?
Now let me start the server application
producer here.
Now just one see the
application.properties. In
application.properties, I have put
enable idempotency equals to true.
Okay?
And here if you see in the producer
config
I I have already created
order events with four partition two
replicas that we have already seen. So,
I'm just starting the
producer application.
Now, let's see
order hyphen events.
So, one uh partition 0 1 2 3 four
partition two replicas each. So, that is
also done properly.
Now, what I have done is I have just
written one API for idempotency check,
very simple. So, here I have just used
same key so that everything goes to the
same partition. Okay? And here I am just
iterating for loop.
Message count is 10. So, 10 times it
just produce a message.
Okay?
So, this is just for testing purpose.
Very simple.
This API count equals to 10. So, 10 time
means 10 messages it will send.
So, I just send
send 10 messages with key. Okay?
Now, here it see the
which partition it goes? Partition two.
It went to the partition two.
And see the offset 0 1 2 3.
Now, partition two, who is the leader?
Partition two leader is three.
So, our one I ID one is controller one,
ID two is controller two, and ID three
is broker one. If you remember, if you
are following the series.
Uh so, means partition goes to the
leader three means broker one.
So, now let's see.
Now, let's see the broker one
logs.
So, here
I am just dumping
the logs. So, here if you see
broker one logs
the path we have already set up temp
partition two order events hyphen two
it's like partition two
and this is the first
log.
So, now here if you see what we are
seeing here.
So,
the header.
First thing is header.
In the header what is the base sequence
is zero.
So, total
10 messages we have sent.
Okay?
In the 10 messages it let's say it goes
into one batch.
The what is the header?
Base is zero.
And the last base sequence is zero.
Last sequence is
nine.
Zero to nine.
Okay?
And what is the producer ID is zero. PID
is
zero.
Now here here if you see these are all
the events.
So, event one
event two event three event four event
five event six event seven event eight
event nine event 10. So, 10 times I'm
looping, right? So, 10 events. Now each
event got a unique sequence sequence
zero sequence one sequence two sequence
three four five six seven eight nine.
And in the header
it just put like base sequence is zero.
And the last sequence is nine.
That's all.
Okay? So,
with this information
the broker can now identify with this
flow that
there is a duplicate or not.
Okay? If let's say retry happen
Okay? And the same
Now what is the next expected? Now,
let's say I am hitting it again. I am
hitting it again one more time.
So, now let's see.
Again, dump the log.
Now, see.
What happened?
So, total 20.
So, this is the first time. Earlier,
base zero.
Last sequence is nine. And now, this is
the one. Next sequence is base sequence
is 10. Last sequence is 9 10. Producer
ID zero.
So, it keep on incrementing. Okay?
Because after this one, it's within the
broker
it has created a map.
It has created the map, and in the last
sequence it was written nine.
Now, the next it was expecting 9 + 1 10.
So, now when I hit again, the batch
Okay? The batch base sequence is 10. So,
it accepted it.
And the last sequence is 19, so it will
update it.
9 10. Now, the next time
when the request or the new batch should
come, it should have the base sequences
should be 20. Then only it will accept
the batch.
Okay?
So, got it? This is clear?
Now, there is one loophole.
What is that one loophole?
If you double-check the step one.
Okay, what was the step one when
producer application start up?
It will ask for unique ID. Broker ask
for controller. Controller generate a
new ID. Return it.
But, there nowhere it is stored that
hey, this producer its ID is 1001.
What happen if this producer restart? It
will again send the request. It will get
a new ID.
So, understand this flow.
Understand the loophole.
Producer first time send give me
producer ID.
It will return 1001.
Now it send the batch.
Topic A, partition zero.
Producer ID is 1001. Base sequence is
let's say three.
And the last sequence is five. Let's say
it send this.
In the log, broker has written it.
Header. Whatever the header Whatever
See, for broker, it just simply write it
whatever you will send me.
Okay?
So, in the header, base sequence three.
Last sequence is five and the producer
ID 1001 I have written.
And in the batch, whatever the events
here I have with event appended with the
sequence, right? Event one, event two,
event three.
Each with base sequence three, four,
five. I have written this.
And also I have updated the map.
Producer ID 1001, topic A, partition P0,
the last sequence I have got is five.
Now what is the next it is expecting? 5
+ 1. So, next base sequence should be
six.
But let's say producer crashed.
Let's say producer got crashed.
And it restarted.
When it restarted, it will again send
hey give me a producer ID. And next time
broker will Broker goes to the
controller. Controller will return let's
say 2001.
Because Controller doesn't maintain any
information that hey this is a producer.
Earlier I have written 1001.
No. With idempotency, this information
is nowhere maintained.
Every time producer ask a request give
me a producer ID, it will generate a new
one.
Now let's say it retry this one. Because
let's say this got crash. It missed the
acknowledgement.
So, it will retry it.
Now let's say that Retry in the sense
because let's say it maintain some DB.
In that one for this information it is
let's say it's
in progress. It is not processed fully
and again create the request and send
it.
So now again batch one again I am
sending topic A
partition P0. Now the process producer
ID is 2001. Earlier it was 1001. But the
base sequence is three, last sequence is
five. The same thing same events I am
sending again. But here now producer ID
is different.
Now if you see the log what would
happen?
It will store it because see the map it
maintain is producer wise.
Producer ID PID topic partition wise.
Now here I am getting different producer
ID 2001.
Now for 2001 producer ID
topic A partition P0 there is no row.
So it will accept it let's say
and it will say that okay the last
sequence I'm expecting is
uh I got is five.
So there is a chance of duplicate.
This is just an example. Uh let's say
whenever the first time it happened
always started from base sequence zero.
But this is for understanding.
Because now the producer ID is changed
it will not be able to identify that hey
five till five I have already written.
Now I am expecting five plus one six
base should be six.
No because producer ID is now different.
So it will store the duplicate.
Let's see this.
Okay. See I have for the producer ID
zero I have already this accepted the
last sequence is 910.
I am just stopping the producer
application starting it again.
I should have gotten new producer ID.
Now I'm sending the request again.
Now let's see
see the dump again.
Okay. So three.
First is producer ID zero,
base sequence zero, last sequence nine.
Correct.
Producer ID zero, base sequence 10, 19.
Correct. But now here if you see new
producer ID I got, producer ID one.
So whenever the you restart the
producer, you get a new producer ID.
And let's say if it retried, if it send
the same batch again, it would be able
to write it again.
Because producer ID is different. This
is just an example I wanted to show you
that there is a loophole.
That when a producer restart, it get a
new PID. Why? Because in case of
idempotency,
controller do not maintain that hey,
this is the producer ID, this is the
producer ID this is the producer, this
is the producer ID I generated before.
No, it doesn't maintain this
information. For that, there is an other
concept called transaction.
I will tell you about transaction after
I complete consumer and consumer groups
set up, too.
Okay? Because
there are scenarios where transaction is
helpful to avoid duplicate.
In this scenario, producer restart
scenario,
and also when consumer fails.
Okay? I will tell you, but
idempotency solves
certain problem, but there is a loophole
which transaction resolves.
So you can say that with transaction,
controller maintains information.
Sorry, that producer let's say
this is the producer one.
This is the ID I generated.
Now if producer restart,
it will always get this ID only.
I will tell you
what all problems this transaction
resolves? Okay, but
after consumer and consumer group setup
because it solves producer
restart issue plus consumer restart
issue also. What if consumer got failed
and got restarted?
Okay, but for that we need to set up the
consumer first.
But I do potency is clear, right?
Now last but not the least
when we set I do potency equals to true
acknowledgement should always be all.
Okay, you know that acknowledge could be
like a zero, could be one and all.
It do not like you can say that when I
do potency equals to true, it should
always be all.
Why?
Because let's say
you are using acknowledge equals to one
means only leader
should get the
update.
Now let's say you send an event
leader follower
leader got the update, but let's say
follower
hasn't pulled it yet
and it got crashed. Leader got crashed.
Now let's say this follower becomes the
leader now.
Okay, now this producer will let's say
send this event again retry because this
leader crashed it didn't send the
acknowledgement.
Now it will resend this batch. Now it
will reach to this
leader different leader.
Okay,
now but this record is not yet copied to
this follower. It doesn't have this
information.
It doesn't have this information so this
will also
get written here.
So that's why we say that when you are
using I do potency the default should be
acknowledgement equals to all because it
makes sure that either all leader and
follower has the same information or
none.
Similarly, the retry is max int. It It
cannot be have like 1 2 3.
Because now retries are safe.
With idempotency, retries are safe. You
can do multiple retries.
So,
when we do idempotency equals to true,
by default,
producer is retries max int.
Internally, sender thread will retry as
much it want. Okay?
But the default now set is max int.
And the third is the max in flight.
It should always be less than equals to
five. You can't set six or seven.
There is one reason if you read the
Kafka documentation,
they specifically mention that
the guarantee,
okay, of this ordering
is only for five sequence.
For this topic, this partition, topic
partition wise, it maintain a sequence,
right? So, it has a buffer only for five
sequences.
Okay? Let's say topic A, partition P0.
Topic A,
partition P1. It just maintain a
buffer of five sequence.
That's all.
Okay?
Why?
Maybe while developing the Kafka broker
and all, they have went through multiple
iteration
to determine what could be the best
number. Because see,
the more the buffer, more retry, more
complexity. Okay? So,
their documentation said that the buffer
they hold is only for the five sequence.
Okay? Means five in flight
request maximum,
you can get guarantee of an ordering.
Okay? if you do six and seven then Kafka
will throw exception here.
If you have set idempotency equals to
true. The number should be less than
equals to five. It will not allow you to
have more than this number because after
that the ordering guarantee is lost.
Okay.
So very important from the point of view
interview and also if you are working
with the Kafka
and like if you're working with
idempotency also then you should be
aware that idempotency is like solves
these two problems. How it solves I show
you.
Okay.
With this base sequence last sequence
and all.
But it also has a loophole that when the
application restart it get a new ID
and if the old batch is sent again it
would be written again.
Okay. And for that
we have to make use of transaction.
That we will see later.
In this any doubt let me know we can
discuss further into the comment
section. Bye.